On this presentation,
we're going to go over
the basics of chest
radiography, and this includes
some of the physics
as well as technique.
Later on, we will go over
some of the more advanced
principles on how to
approach chest radiography.
So, the objectives are
to understand the basic
principles of x-rays, understand
some basic normal chest
radiographic anatomy,
which we'll sort of glance
over, and I'll highlight
important points on this
PowerPoint for different
things you should know,
either for exams or in real
life when you're on your
clinical rotations, which
are shortly approaching.
And then we'll
formulate an approach
on how to read
chest radiographs.
So we're only going to
glance at the physics.
This is not a physics
course, but an x-ray
beam is generated by
passing an electron beam
through a vacuum between
the anode and cathode.
The positive charge
anode tracks the
electron and that
generates the x-ray.
we do measure and this
is important for those
radiologists and go to
radiology we measure the
effective dose of a x-ray
or radiation general as a
millisievert the effective
dose is what we usually
describe when we encounter
the x-ray with the
entire body and we want to
know about any soft tissue
damage or the development
of cancer later in life
which was subject to a
recent journal article.
The effective dose takes
into how sensitive the
different tissues are in
radiation and how much that x
-ray will affect that specific
soft tissue structure.
So according to recent
estimates, the average
person in the U.S.
receives an effective dose
of about 3 mS per year
from natural radiation,
that includes cosmic
radiation, and it varies
depending where you're
at, Colorado, New
Mexico, more than those
living at the sea level.
Just so for reference,
a coast-to-coast
flight round trip is
about 0.03 millisieverts
due to cosmic
exposure to radiation.
So overall, the more
important point is that
one adult chest radiograph,
which is about 0.1
millisieverts, is the
same as about living 10
days of natural bacterial
radiation that we get
in our daily life. I put
a link here if you're
just curious about
knowing how much radiation
a specific structure
has in an imaging study.
So, as the S-rays pass
through an object,
based on the density of
the object, the X-rays
will be either absorbed
and or scattered.
It is that degree of
absorption of the X-ray which
creates the image on the
film that we will see.
So, X-ray can pick up
a couple densities, the
darkest on top being air,
and then fat, and then
soft tissue and fluid we
sort of group together,
And that fluid, as
I noted down here,
can be pus, blood,
or just simple
fluid. It all has
its same appearance.
Then the calcium, sort
of, if you have something
which is calcific
tendinosis of the shoulder.
And then bones, extra
contrast, and metal. And the
widest structure would be
metal. So you can see here on
this radiograph, this person
has a AICD pacemaker. And
here's the lead. And we can
see that this density is
the widest on the radiograph
compared to that of the
bone. the soft tissue of
the heart the aorta then the
least dense would be the
gas soft tissues as well as
that in the trachea going
down into the bronchi so all
that physics basically creates
shadow and is that shadow
that we are looking for
we look at on radiographs
as radiologists so one of
the understanding of key
understandings is you have
to have different densities
next to each other for contrast
to see the image so this
difference in densities
allows that contrast to be
seen and noted so if there's
not enough contrast or
difference in densities
between adjacent structures no
sharp margins or structures
on the image or objects will
be blend together and this
is the silhouette sign and
i highlight this because
this is important to know.
So here is a forearm
radiograph. This is the radius,
the ulna, humerus,
metacarpals, and carpal bones.
And we all know basically
from your anatomy, you know
there's different flexor
tendon groups, muscles,
but all that muscles have
the same density. So that's
why we cannot decide from
radiograph the difference in
those flexor densities. Now,
I can see the difference
between the bone and the
muscles, but I can't see
the difference between the
individual muscle groups
because they have all that same
density, and hence they are
silhouetted. So, once again,
for us to see structures
and radiographs, they have
to have different densities
next to each other, and
we're going to go over this
more in detail with specifics
to the chest, but the form
is an easy structure to
look at with the different
muscle groups that you guys
remember from your anatomy
class so you can only see
a structure is only visible
in radiographs when it has
a different density next
to it things that have the
same density next to it you
cannot see so i can see the
heart because there's lungs
surrounding it there's
different densities i can see
the ribs different from the
soft tissues because there
are different densities
But I cannot see the difference
between the liver and
the diaphragm. So the liver
being here, you can see the
inferior marginal liver.
There's a different density
of fat next to it. But when
it gums up liver being soft
tissue density, diaphragm
being soft tissue density,
I cannot see the difference
in those densities because
they're the same. They're
the soft tissue density.
So once again, you
need two different
densities next to each
other to see them.
incidentally note we can
see that there's a metallic
densities over here these
are colesectomy clips in
someone who had their
gallbladder removed once again
a different density from
that of the liver so here's
a chest x-ray this is the
heart these are the lungs
we can see on this chest
radiograph the difference
between the heart and
lungs because the lungs gas
density is different from that
of the soft tissue density
of the heart in a different
patient, we have the
heart density on this side,
here's the right heart
border, but on the left
side, we do not see well this
left heart border like we
do in this patient. And the
reason being is that this
person has a pneumonia in
their lingual lobe. If you
remember back to your 90
days, your lingular lobe
lives right against that
left heart border. So as I
said in the beginning when
we went over densities soft
tissue density includes
those of fluid pus and
blood that's all grouped
together so in this person
they have pus and blood or pus
or blood or something in
their alveoli fluid which
is obscuring that left heart
border it's silhouetting
that left heart border
so different density over
here left heart border from
gas similar densities next
to each other we can't see
that left heart border.
So we lose that expected
interface normally when we
have structures of density
next to each other and
no boundary can be seen when
you have similar densities.
Once again, different
densities, lung, heart,
same density next to each
other, heart, pus and blood
in its alveoli that's
silhouetting it. And this is an
important concept that
you're gonna need to know for
exams, for life, when you're
looking at radiographs.
So we're going to go over
couple of little techniques
now we're going to
talk about different
projections of the film,
what's a PA and AP and what
that actually means,
inspiratory effort, penetration
of films, and the
positioning and rotation,
and then we'll go into
some anatomy at the end.
So when we're talking about
different films we're talking
about PA film, that means
that the x-ray is going
from posterior to anterior,
and then we have an AP film
which means that the x-ray
is going from anterior,
anterior, the anterior part
of the chest, to posterior.
Here's the x-ray unit.
This is the detector
or where the film is
at. Same thing here. X
-ray unit, the detector
where the film is at.
This is an important
concept you're going to have
to know going forward and
what the difference between
these techniques are and
what they actually mean.
So an AP film is less
advantaged, or we don't like
to do them as much. They're
typically done in ICU
patients for trauma patients.
And the reason we don't
like to do these AP films
where the x-rays coming
from anterior to posterior
is because one of the
structures we like to look
at in the chest is the heart.
When the x-ray
beams come in, the
heart being an
anterior structure,
the x-rays as they come in
and hit this will diverge
and make a shadow of the
heart on the film itself.
This shadow, since
it's an anterior
structure, as the
x-rays come in,
because it's anterior,
it allows more time
for those x-rays to
diverge, therefore causing
magnification of the
heart on the film.
As opposed to a PA film,
where the heart being
an anterior structure,
as these x-rays come in,
there's less chance of
divergence of those x-rays
to form the shadow of
the heart on the film,
therefore there's less
magnification of the heart.
And that's important
when you're looking at
chest radiographs to
see if that person's
heart is enlarged
or not, whether your
differential diagnosis
being cardiomegaly from
CHF or other etiologies.
So once again, posterior
anterior, x-rays are
coming from posterior to
anterior, less magnification
of the heart. Anterior
to posterior, x-rays
are coming in, more
magnification of the heart.
The PA film that the
patient needs to be
actually be standing,
the AP film the patient
can be standing or they're
laying down. This is
typically they're usually
laying down for these AP films.
So this is the same patient
that came in. Here's
your PA film. This is the
heart border. Right heart
border. Left heart border.
If we look at this and
we compare it on the same
patient on the AP film,
here is the heart
border on this side.
Here's the heart border
on this side. So you can
tell that there is magnification
that the heart is more
magnified on this view.
The same thing applies to
the mediastinum. this would
be the mediastinal area
over here. You can see
how thin and narrow it is.
However, in the AP
film, we can see that
there's magnification
because the mediastime also
being anterior causes
that magnification.
So in a trauma patient, this
would be more concerning
for maybe a mediastinal
process like an hematoma
in someone who had
trauma. So that's why
the difference between
the PA or knowing what
the film is, PA versus
AP is very important.
So how can you actually
tell in the film? Well,
sometimes there's subtle
hilt in the films.
So on a PA film,
x-ray unit, x-ray
detector, x-rays are going
to come from posterior
anterior, so we know
it's PA, we can see
that the patient here
has their arms or their
hands on their hips.
That causes the scapula to be
moved out of the field of view.
So we don't see
much scapular border
because of the position
of the PA film.
As opposed to an AAP
film, your ICU patient,
someone who's just
standing normally, you have
your arms out their
side, you can see their
arms are down at their
side. And then we can see
that here, this is the
scapula border over
here, and this is the
scapula border over here.
So for an AP film, we
will often see scapula on
the chest. For a PA
film, the scapula will be
abducted out of the field
of view, and we don't have
much scapula to be seen
on the radiograph itself.
So AP, we see scapula.
PA, we see maybe a little bit
of scapula, but not that much.
Now, this is not
a steadfast rule.
The steadfast rule is
when the tech labels it.
You can see here this
is a portable, portable
being AP film. That
should be an AP film, and
we should be seeing
scapula, but we do not.
The scapula is, however,
abducted out of the field
of view because this
technologist had the
patient move their arms
out in a similar position,
so the scapula we don't
see on the AP film here.
So that's AP and PPA. we're
going to go over inspiratory
effort and how that affects
the film itself and then
penetration and then
patient rotation and anatomy
last so same patient again
so here's your pa film this
person take a good breath
and we're going to go over
what a good breath means
that's nine to ten post your
ribs i'm going to show you
how to count the ribs in a
second this is someone who
didn't take a great breath
and you can see that the
heart looks larger as well so
that also adds in for the AP
film. So you get magnification
or exaggeration of structure
with poor breath on
the radiograph as well as
if it's AP or PA film. Well,
how do you actually count
the ribs? So I'm going to
show you on this film here
because it's a better film.
The easiest way to count the
ribs is if you can imagine
here, your eye probably
creates a circle over
here. And it's probably
creating a circle over here.
And if it's not, just
hallucinate with me that it is.
This circle right
here is formed by the
difference of density
of the lung to the
first rib. This is the
first rib over here.
If you follow this first
rib back, it ends right
here. This is the first
rib. So that would be the
first rib. And then what
we will do is we will count
laterally all the other
ribs. So here's one, here's
two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine,
ten ribs. So we count
the ribs that are
above the diaphragm.
So this person has ten
posterior ribs, and
we count posterior
ribs because it's the
easier ribs to count.
Again, on this side,
I forms a circle. I
follow the less dense part
of the circle. I'm like,
oh, it gets wider over
here. That's that
first rib. I'm going to
follow it back. Here's
that first rib. A little
point picking up over
here. And then I'm going
to count laterally. So
here's that first rib.
This is the second rib.
The third rib, fourth,
fifth, sixth, seventh,
eighth, ninth, tenth.
And 11 ribs just above
that mid-clavicular line.
So that's how you count
ribs on a chest radiograph.
The less ribs you have,
the poorer the inspiratory
effort. When you have
poor inspiratory effort,
everything sort of gets
squished down, and we
have magnification or
exaggeration of the cardiac
silhouette and mediastinum
because of that.
In terms of penetration
of the film, an optimally
penetrated film, penetration
means how many x-rays are
actually getting through
this patient and going to
the cassette. and this is
determined by the technologists
when they enter that in
the machine so as the
x-rays come through this
is an optimally penetrated
film and what do I mean
by that well I can see the
end plates of the vertebral
bodies it's probably
easier to see here I can
see the end plate of the
vertebral body here's the
inferior end plate of the
superior end plate of the
vertebral body I can see the
disc space in between and
that's what we're looking
for we're looking to see
if we can see those disc
spaces in In a film where
not enough x-rays are
getting through, and we call
that underpenetrated, so
there's an under amount of x
-rays going to that cassette,
the film looks whiter.
With an overpenetrated
film, too
many x-rays are
getting through.
We see the vertebral bodies
a lot better, but what
happens is those x-rays as
they're going through are
saturating out the lungs, so
we don't see the lungs well.
Penetration is a very
important topic when
we're going to look for
structures that potentially
can be occurring behind
the heart. So over
here, I can see behind
the heart and I can
see the diaphragm in a
well-penetrated film.
In an under-penetrated
film where not enough x
-rays are going through,
I could not tell you if
there's a mass or pneumonia
or something that's
on the film that may be
causing that symptom.
Similarly, in an awfully
penetrated film, I can see
the long markings, which
are all these little white
lines here, and I can
evaluate the lungs for masses
or pneumonias, nodules,
but someone who has too
many x-rays going through,
I can't see any of the
lung parenchyma. I can't
see any of those white lines
like I can on an optimally
penetrated film. So we
cannot evaluate the lung
parenchyma optimally here.
So, moving on, we're
going to talk about
position and rotation
and why that's important.
So, how do we determine
position and rotation
of film? What we're
going to do is
we're going to look at
the spinous process,
And we're going to
compare the spines
paralysis versus the
clavicular heads.
Here's one clavicular
head on the right.
Here's the other
clavicular head. They
should be equidistant.
So if I go from here
to here and here to
here, in a perfectly
positioned film, they
should be equidistant.
On this film, you can see
that the right side is a
little closer from the clavicle
to the spines paralysis.
And this is a little
wider. So this
person does have a
degree of rotation.
Now, that can vary significantly
depending on the film
itself. So something like
this, this person is very
rotated. First, it's an
underpenetrated film, right?
We don't see a lot of x-ray.
We don't see anything behind
the heart over here. We
can't see the spine itself.
So it makes it challenging
in and of itself. And then
if we look here, here's the
spines process over here.
Here's the clavicle. These
are very close together.
Here's the spines process.
Here's the other margin
of the clavicle. These
are very far apart. And
that's important when
you're looking at the aorta
itself, because in a patient
rotated, we can exaggerate
an aorta, and sometimes
it can look aneurysmal
or looks like it's causing
deviation of the trachea,
which we'll go over on
the pathology section,
artificially just
because of that rotation.
The same thing applies when
we have a pneumothorax.
We may under account for
any mediastinal shift in
the tension pneumothorax
because of that rotation.
so that's the
technical parts of it
the important things
to know are the
silhouette sign penetration
film counting ribs
as well as rotation
for the anatomy i'm not
going to go over too
much in the anatomy i
highlight some important
structures that you should
know you should know
what the aortic **** is
this structure right
here is the aortic ****
the aortic **** should
always be on the left
side this is the left
heart border the left
heart board is formed by
the ventricle, the right
heart board is formed
by the right atrium.
This is the costophrenic
angle, and this
is the cardiophrenic
angle over here.
On the lateral film,
there's a couple
of structures that's important.
One, this is the sternum,
this white line right here
coming down. This is the
sternum. If you're ever going
to go into ER surgery and
you have a lateral film of
the chest, you always want
to evaluate for the sternum
to make sure there's no
fractures of the and someone
who has a motor vehicle
accident, so we're going to
look at this white line,
make sure it's not straight.
The structure next that
you're going to look at is
this retrosternal clear
space, and this should just
have gas in the space. This
should just be gas there.
You cannot see this on the
frontal film because the
sternum overlies it. The
sternum overlies that frontal
film, so we can't see it.
Also, because it's two
-dimensional, we can't see it,
so you have to look over here
in this retrosternal clear
space on the lateral film.
This should be the
aric arch coming
down to the descending aorta.
We have your right
ventricle, which is the most
anterior over here. That's
why if you get stabbed in the
chest, the right ventricles
they want to look at.
And then we can find
the costofranic angles
here. Here's one
costofranic angle over here.
Here's the other
costofranic angle right down
here. And those are the
structures that we look
at. So for when you're
looking at a lateral
radiograph, we're going
to evaluate the sternum.
Retro-sternal clear
space, we're going
to evaluate the
costofranic angles.
On a lateral radiograph,
we can see on the frontal
radiograph, we know what's
the right hemidiaphram. This
is the right side of the
patient. This is the left
side of the patient. We know
this is the left hemidiaphram.
This is the right hemidiaphram.
But on the lateral
view, they're all overlapping.
So how do we tell?
Well, there's a
couple things you can
do. The right should
be higher than the
left. So this is the
right hemidiaphram.
The left hemidiaphram
can have the gas bubble
underneath it. So this would
be the left hemidiaphram.
But sometimes those are
not steadfast rules if you
don't see the gas in the
diaphragm well or maybe
at their same level the
divers at the same level or
the size apparent the
elevation so what we can do
is we can use the silhouette
sign and what that
implies is that the right
hemorrhoid diaphragm you
will see all the way out
from the posterior margin
the cost of rank angle all
the way anteriorly to the
sternum by the left we
will only see where the
heart is not touching it
where the heart touches it
it becomes blurred, and
we can use the silhouette
sign in that respect to
help us find the difference
between the right and
left hemorrhoid diaphragm.
So, here's a better
example. How do you tell
what's the right and
what's the left hemorrhoid
diaphragm? They're all
together here, but if I
were using the silhouette
sign, I know this is the
right hemorrhoid diaphragm
because I can see
it all the way over
anteriorly, and I can follow
back, this is the right
hemorrhoid diaphragm.
The left-hemi diaphragm,
I don't see here because
the heart soft tissue
structure is sitting on
the diaphragm soft tissue
structure right here.
But when the heart is not
sitting on it anymore,
right here, that is that
left-hemi diaphragm.
So the silhouette
sign, once again.
I'm not going to really
spend any time on brachial
pulmonary anatomy. I'm
sure this is exhausted in
your anatomy lectures
from last year. There's a
mnemonic if you want to go
over the segments of it.
So I'm not going to
really touch on this. Same
thing, you just have
to remember that you've
grouped the lingular lobe
with the upper lobe over
here, and there is also
a mnemonic for that.
I will touch a little
bit on fissures.
The right side has
two fissures, has
a minor fissure and
major fissure. The
left side just has
a major fissure.
So the minor fissure
travels horizontally.
The major fissures
travel obliquely. So on a
frontal film, we can see
the minor fissure. It looks
like a thin white line,
while the major fissures
are obliquely oriented,
and you see them only
on the lower radiograph.
You can see the minor
fissure or horizontal
fissure on the lower
radiograph as well. Once
again, it has a horizontal
wide line that you're
going to be looking for.
Well, what's the important
of these fissures?
On the right side, they
separate the lobes.
The middle lobe is
separated from the upper
lobe with the minor
fissure. The upper and
middle lobes are
separated from the lower
lobe by the major fissure
on the right side.
so these are important
schematics that you're going
to need to know this as
well as these films I'm
going to show you they may
show up on exams or other
important things in life
in your rotation so right
upper lobe you want to
know that this is the
right upper lobe has a
straight border because of the
horizontal fissure has a
straight border over here
on the lateral film because
of the major fissure
the right middle lobe has
a straight upper margin
because of that minor
fissure and a straight
lower margin because
of the oblique fissure.
So you're going to want to
know this type of appearance
of a right middle lobe.
These images are important
in the highlight in red
for your viewing pleasure.
Here's a right lower
lobe, major fissure, sharp
border because of that
oblique fissure. So this is
all the right lower lobe.
Right lower lobe goes up
pretty high. So you can
see it goes all the way
up here, but it's separated
by that major fissure.
The left side only has one
fissure, has a major fissure.
It separates the upper
lobe from the lower lobe.
So this is all left
upper lobe, because
the left upper lobe
will also include the
linear lobe, which
lives right against that
left-hand border. So
all left upper lobe,
sharp posterior margin
because of the major fissure.
And then left lower
lobe, sharp anterior
margin because of the
major fissure. And the
left lower lobe, this
is all left lower lobe.
So, another important
schematic here, you can see,
and then here, this would
be the auric ****. Another
thing that I want you to
recognize on films, the
right middle lobe adjacent
to the right heart border,
the lingual lobe adjacent
to the left heart border.
I want to touch briefly
on the mediastinum.
I want you guys
to know the auric
****, as I mentioned before.
You can see that there's
often a bump. There's
three bumps. There's
the auric ****, there's
the main pulmonary
artery outflow tract, and
then the left ventricle
itself. And you want
to know that this is
the left ventricle, the
right atrium was over
here on the frontal film.
In the Lyle film,
once again, left
ventricle posteriorly,
right ventricle
anteriorly, important
structures to know.
Right surperineals,
clear space, sternum,
and then the classifying
angles. And then
we can decipher our
diaphragm space and the
silhouette sign, which
I mentioned before.
So, just as a
teaser for the next
lecture, how do
I approach films?
is I'm going to assess
the quality of film.
The next thing I'm going
to do is for tubes, lines,
and any hardwares because
those can often be misplaced.
And then I start with
an approach. I look at
the upper abdomen first
to make sure I miss
any free air. I can
follow the diaphragms.
Then I'll look at the bone
and soft tissues as I go
through, and I'll make sure
I can count all the ribs.
And I can see the ribs,
and then they have smooth
margins, no fractures. I'll
look at the soft tissues to
make sure they have a normal
grayish density to them.
And then I'll
look at the heart.
I'll actually
measure the heart.
I'll look at the
hilum over here, the
hilum over here, as
well as the mediastine,
make sure there's
no abnormalities.
And then I'll look at the
lungs and pleura. I'll
evaluate one lung, then I'll
evaluate the other lung,
and then I'll look at them
together for symmetry.
Now, a lot of students
like the ABCDE method,
because it keeps it very
simple when you're first
starting on radiographs.
So the ABCDE, A is airway,
you want to follow the
trachea, you want to make
sure it's midline, and
the right and mid-left
stem bronchus, you want
to follow it to branching.
B is bones. Once again,
you're going to look at the
bones, make sure there's
no fractures of the bones.
No fractures, you can see
the clavicles over here.
C is heart, and then
you're going to look at
the heart, make sure
it's not enlarged. It
also implies the
mediastinum at that point.
D is diaphragm. You're
going to look for the
diaphragms and the curved.
You're going to look
for the cost of frank
angles, which are not
on this film, but you'll
look at the cost of
frank angles. Also, you
evaluate for free air.
And then E is everything
else. So you can look at the
lungs in that. Some people
add an F to it for lung
fields, but you'll evaluate
the lung markings, you'll
evaluate for symmetry, you'll
evaluate for pneumothorax.
So that's pretty much
the physics of chest
radiographs. We'll
have another lecture
when we go over some
pathologies. Thanks.